Modern views of gladiator battles are
incredibly wrong. Not just when it comes
to the common tropes like the infamous
thumbs down symbol, slave combatants are
fighting to the death, but on a grander
scale of truly reflecting the massive
scope of this juggernaut of the ancient
entertainment industry. From the
promotional campaigns involving weeks of
advertising, and teaser trailers
to the pre-event tailgating where people
bought snacks, collected merch, placed
bets, and purchased souvenirs like
gladiator sweat. The sophisticated
system for managing crowd flows, and
keeping them cool.
The artistry of putting on games with
themed events and props that could last
days, weeks, or months on end. the
exoticism of animal hunts, female
gladiator duels, and monkey cavalry
battles.
The engineering of flooding the coliseum
to host naval gladiator battles,
or simply switching venues to an entire
lake for true fleet fleet action. The
t-shirt cannon prize system where you
could win an elephant, and on and on.
Once you start to scratch the surface,
the real history of the arena truly
boggles the mind. So, in this series,
let's bring it all to life. We can begin
with the rise of the gladiators.
You can lead your own war host into
battle with today's sponsor, Mountain
Blade 2: Bannerlord, which is now 60%
off the base game and 30% off the War
Sales Naval DLC through July 9th.
Mountain Blade is a series I've been
playing for a long time now and deeply
enjoy. Not only for the awesome
gameplay, but the truly unique history
nerd experience of being able to
actually take part in a medieval battle.
The latest war sales update introduces
seaborn village raids, which are an
awesome new battle type to live out your
Viking fantasy. With a crew of at least
15, a shallow draft vessel, and coastal
or river access, you or the AI can now
take the fight to enemy shores across 16
new coastal battlefield scenes.
Defending militias may fold immediately
to your pressure, allowing you to loot
freely, but if they find their nerves,
you'll find yourself in a mission for
control of the beach head. It's a great
addition to the campaign that deepens
the gameplay of an already amazing
experience.
So whether you're a new or returning
player, now is a great time to get back
in on the action during the Steam summer
sale, where you can get Mountain Blade 2
at 60% off and war sales at 30% off now
through July 9th. Enjoy.
As with most things in the realm of
Rome's early mytho history, the origins
of gladiators are a bit unclear.
Nonetheless, most Roman historians seem
to converge on the same idea that the
first gladiators were slaves bought
specifically to carry out a set oferary
rights called monera or games. These
held that the dead, particularly war
leaders, must be properly honored
through displays of courage.
Gladiatorial matches thus became the
manifestation of this desire to
commemorate the passing of great men.
But the Romans were not the first to
invent this practice. Rather, it seems
to have been adopted from other older
cultures of the region such as the
Atruscans.
Obviously, only wealthy families could
afford to uphold such extravagant
traditions. Games therefore often took
place on private property. However, it
was soon found to be more convenient to
host such messy events in the forum
itself. Here, a temporary oval surface
would be laid out called the arena,
which literally means sand. It is on
these grounds that slaves would fight,
often to the death, next to the funeral
p of the deceased, in what was
essentially a theatric form of human
sacrifice.
Such blood sports always seemed to draw
audiences throughout history, and Rome's
elites were quick to realize that they
could take advantage of this fact. Thus,
the lower classes were soon invited in
as spectators. In these gladiatorial
moon era, people might crowd around the
sidelines, but for larger events,
temporary wooden amphitheaters would be
constructed. In addition, new
festivities would be tacked on, such as
public giveaways, feasts, and other
events. Thus, the games were slowly
introduced into Roman life [music] as
primarily religious ceremonies with
entertainment value taking a backseat.
However, this would slowly be reversed
over the course of the Republican
period. For instance, our earliest
records of a funeral game dates back to
264 BC, right at the very start of the
Punic Wars. At this time, gladatorial
mona were often single day events with
just a few fighters. The funeral games
for Desimus Brutus Junius Ska, for
instance, featured a total of just three
pairs of gladiators, which at the time
was considered grandiose.
The slave fighters in these early days
were caricatures of Rome's enemies and
titled as such. There were the Sam
Knights, the Gauls, and the Thrians,
each of which faced off with their own
particular weapons, armor, and fighting
styles. This brought an added layer of
intrigue as matches could now be framed
by a theme or narrative. It was even
popular to put on hypothetical matchups
where nerdy Romans could reenact what it
would be like if two otherwise unknown
[music] forces fought in real life.
Thus, we see the inevitable pivot
towards entertainment begin. This would
truly accelerate towards the end of the
Punic Wars. It is now that the
generation of Rome's conquering elite
sought to honor their fathers and
themselves with ever more extravagant
displays of self agrandisement. Thus,
the humble moon era of old evolved into
full-blown performances with funeral
games lasting multiple days and
featuring up to 100 fighting pairs.
Along with their scale came added
complexity. Huge stands had to be
erected, seat numbers assigned, and
tickets distributed. By now, the games
were becoming thoroughly commercialized.
But still, they held onto a vestage of
their original purpose. It was common,
for instance, to say that such and such
games were being held in memory of a
particular family member, even if their
passing had occurred months or even
years prior. By the late Republic of the
1st century BC, though, things got even
crazier. It is in this period that
Rome's politicians competed fiercely for
the public's attention with an arms race
of elaborate spectacles. This was
especially true for the two annually
elected eiles whose responsibility was
to fund, organize, and host each year's
ludai or public games. Technically, they
were given a fixed budget by the Senate,
but individuals would often invest
ludicrous amounts of their own funds to
make the most memorable games possible
[music] in the hopes of skyrocketing
their political careers. Making this all
possible was a whole network of private
merchants and schools which churned out
fighters for the arena. However, the
industry proved dangerously unregulated
when one of their number, a man named
Spartacus, led a widescale slave revolt.
Yet, even this traumatic event did
little to curb Rome's appetite for
continued blood sport. For example, less
than a decade later, Julius Caesar made
quite the name for himself by hosting
games of such a scale that they blew
away all those which had come before.
Set in 65 BC in commemoration of his
late father, they saw the city
transformed by elaborate decorations,
processions, and games that featured an
unprecedented 320 gladiator pairs
dressed in silver armor. The madman
actually planned on having even more
gladiators than that were it not for a
cap imposed by a fearful Senate. Civil
war put a damper on such festivities,
but when peace returned, they would come
roaring back to life. As with most
things in this period of transition,
though, they would be overhauled and
co-opted by Augustus. For instance,
while notable Romans were still given
responsibility for organizing the games,
the emperor always had final say on
their decisions and was the one signing
all the checks. Meanwhile, facilities
such as the gladiator schools were taken
over by the Roman state and pumped full
of money. Imperial cash similarly flowed
to fund the construction of new arenas
such as Rome's first [music] permanent
amphitheater in the campus marshes. Many
of these likewise began to pop up across
the empire. But the king of them all
would be the 50,000 capacity colosum
built by Vespasian in the late 1st
century AD. With its inauguration came
100 days of festivities and the true
beginning of the golden age of the
gladiator.
Games in this era would be hosted in
Rome multiple times a year stretching
out weeks if not months at a time. These
were events of monumental proportion
featuring men and animals from every
corner of the empire with no expenses
spared. After all, gladiatorial matches
were now part of a major industry which
was key to the socopolitical governance
of Rome. Here the game served as a
useful way for emperors to flex their
might while at the same time keeping the
populace happy with a regular dose of
bread and circuses. Let us now take a
look at what this entailed.
We can begin with the gladiators
themselves. These primarily came from
three sources: slaves, criminals, and
free volunteers. For most of Rome's
history, it was the slaves who provided
the bulk of the gladiatorial ranks. At
first, these would largely have been
prisoners of war and were therefore men
with some fighting experience.
Naturally, they seemed to have been
kitted out with the gear most closely
resembling that of their homeland.
Spartacus, for instance, is famously
referenced as fighting in the garb of
Thrian. However, as time passed, slaves
were increasingly born into their
position rather than having been
captured. Such youths were not as
marshially inclined and were therefore
often sent to the gladiator schools to
be groomed for their futures in the
arena. This would involve years of
training meant to develop their skills
and fighting styles. Thus, they spent
most of their lives in the Lutus. Even
those who were eventually granted their
freedom might return to the only home
they knew to make a living in the
gladiatorial industry until they were
aged out or killed.
Another major source of gladiators came
in the form of criminals. These were
people who had been spared death and had
instead been sentenced to a prescribed
number of years in the Lutus. This was
considered merciful as it would give
convicts a chance at redemption through
honorable combat. However, it was quite
idealistic thinking. In reality, the
schools wasted little time or resources
training such men. Thus, they largely
served as cannon fodder fit for the
slaughter of the arena when blood was
required. It was these convict fighters
who made up the hapless hordes of bad
guys that the trained gladiators could
defeat and mass. But if one somehow
survived their sentence, they could walk
free. Often, however, it was again the
best fighters that made it out, and
these in turn used their freedom to
reinlist for profit. This now gets us to
the last major source of gladiators, the
volunteers. Free Roman citizens were not
immune to the lure of the crowds and the
promises of fame and fortune. Thus, some
actually sought to descend from the
stands into the arena itself. But
entering a gladiatorial school was no
simple matter akin to joining a sports
team. By entering a lutus, you were
signing away your freedoms, rights, and
reputation. To join, you first had to
register with the Roman government and
make a formal oath, pledging to remain
true to the job in the face of burning,
imprisonment, or death by the sword.
Additionally, you would become an
infamous, forbidden the rights of a
Roman citizen for the rest of your life.
You couldn't vote, couldn't run for
office, couldn't provide testimony in
court, couldn't make a will, couldn't
enter certain temples, couldn't partake
in certain rights, and were no longer
shielded from corporal punishment.
Essentially, you were now in the same
category as dancers, prostitutes,
[music]
and those who sold their bodies for the
pleasure of others. Thus, once in the
Lutus, these former free men were
considered equals to the slave
gladiators.
Yet, despite all the horrors and dangers
of becoming a gladiator, it did have its
upsides. Successful gladiators were rich
and famous people who were adored by the
crowds of the Roman Empire. They were
the ultimate sex symbols of the ancient
world to the point that a gladiator's
blood was considered a key ingredient in
love and fertility potions. Weapons that
had killed gladiators were also in
extremely high demand by women who would
keep them as a talisman or good luck
charm to enhance their own sex lives.
Gladiators were proud of this celebrity
status, flaunting it as much as they
were able. Surviving graffiti for
instance includes lines like Coladus the
thrian makes the girls moan or cresence
the net holds the hearts of all the
girls.
Yet while some fits of passion were
certainly consensual at the end of the
day gladiators were not in control of
their own destiny. If someone wanted to
pay to have sex with them this was just
a part of the job just as much as if
someone wanted to pay to see them bleed
in the arena. But we shouldn't think
that the gritty nature of a gladiator's
life was reserved for the poor and the
desperate. It turns out that we have
tons of records of wealthy Romans
clamoring to hop into the arena.
Emperors such as Nero and Comeodus made
a spectacle playing the role of a
gladiator while all manner of
politicians could be seen fighting as
well. However, while this might have
stirred up gossip, the real problem
seems to have arisen from young nobles
who stampeded into the arena, tarnishing
the reputation of many powerful
families. The issue proved so severe
that the Senate even had to step in with
a formal law in 1980. This senator's
consultum reads as follows. Quote, "It
pleased the senators that no one should
bring onto the stage a senator's son,
daughter, grandson, granddaughter,
great-grandson, great-granddaughter, or
any male whose father or grandfather,
whether paternal or maternal, or
brother, or any female whose husband or
father, or grandfather, whether paternal
or maternal, or brother, had ever
possessed the right of sitting in the
seats reserved for the equestrians, or
induced them by means of a fee to appear
in such a venue, or to snatch the plumes
of gladiators, or take the rutus off
anyone one or to take part in any
similar subordinate capacity.
But even if the top of the social ladder
was restrained from joining in, the rest
of society provided more than enough
supply for the games. In doing so, they
would take to the sands as one of the
various flavors of combatant. Let's now
talk about these different types of
gladiators.
Traditionally, this had begun by having
gladiators fight according to
stereotypical depictions of various
warrior cultures. As mentioned
previously, you had your Samites, your
Thrians, your Gauls, your Greeks, your
Britons on chariots and more. However,
over time, it grew a bit offensive to
depict former enemies turned to allies
in this way. It was also somewhat
boring, and so the Romans innovated.
Given their love of war and feats of
ingenuity, this was a match made in
heaven. Gladiator contests therefore
quickly became the Roman equivalent of
real life role- playinging games where
warriors could be kitted out with all
kinds of gear and pitted against one
another in PvP. Some were armed with
swords, spears, axes, bows, javelins,
daggers, trident, harpoons, hooks, nets,
and more. You could become the master of
one, dual wield a set, or mix and match.
Defensively, gladiators might carry a
large shield, a small shield, or none at
all. They might be fully encased in
heavy armor or sparingly adorned with
gear that looked cool but made sure to
show off bare chests and loin cloths.
Other times they might be virtually
naked. In addition, gladiators could
fight on foot, on horse, or on chariot.
The possibilities here were endless.
Naturally, some loadouts were considered
overpowered and would therefore be
handicapped in some way. Cicero, for
instance, mentions how powerful
charioters might be blindfolded. The
meta, so to speak, was thus constantly
evolving as tweaks were made. The Romans
were deeply invested in arguments about
the state of the competition. It
wouldn't be uncommon to hear these
ancient nerds go on for hours about
various theoretical matchups. Luckily
for them, such hypotheticals could be
put to the test in the arena itself.
Just like modern gamers though, they
counted the victories as clear signs of
the superiority of their favorite
warrior type, but complained about any
losses having been due to the cheating
or the OP nature of their rivals. To
bring some order to the chaos, the
industry thus gradually adopted a sort
of standard for the classification of
gladiators and how they should best be
matched up. Every gladiator, therefore,
was groomed to a different style, making
it a part of their character. Each man
identified with his classification and
they were housed according to class
within the gladiator barracks itself.
Classic examples include the Thrian, the
Mio, and the Retiaras, but we have
records of dozens of other types with
many more that simply go unrecorded.
Let's review a few of these.
The Thrian wore a small shield, thigh
length greaves, and a broad- rimmed
helmet with a distinctive crest, and was
armed with a curved Sika sword. They
were thought to be versatile fighters
who could take a hit but move quickly.
Against them was often paired the
Murmmo. These were men with heavy armor,
a shield, and a short sword that had
originally been derived from the Gallas
class of fighters named after the Gauls.
As compared to the Thrians, they were
far better protected, but moved slower
and tired out more quickly. This was
exactly the sort of dynamic matchup that
the Romans were looking for. Another
classic matchup involved the Retiaris.
Modeled after a fisherman, he wielded a
net alongside a spear or trident.
Offensively, they were quite powerful
and thus were left with little defense
aside from an arm and shoulder guard.
Even still, they easily dominated
matches and thus were paired against a
special counter called the Seutor. This
so-called chaser carried a large shield,
protective armor, and a special helmet.
It was rounded so as to avoid being
caught by the net with eyeholes small
enough to block jabs from the trident.
But even this was sometimes not enough
to contend with the fast-moving
Retiaris. A popular format was therefore
to have a single net fighter placed at
top a mound or bridge which he was to
defend against two encroaching Seurus.
As with the previous matchup, it made
for an exciting asymmetrical fight.
Other gladiator types worth mentioning
include the Hiplomac, a proxy for the
Greek hoplight, who had a spear, a
sword, and a small buckler. There was
also the provocator styled after a
Republican legionary who wore a small
chest plate, helmet, leg armor, large
shield, and bore a gladius sword. Other
gladiators had less direct historical
precedent, such as the brass knuckle
wielding Kestas or the skzer, who dual
wielded weapons that some have even
theorized were encased in metal tubes
like something straight out of a fantasy
game. Beyond this were all kinds of
ranged and mounted gladiators.
This massive variety of different
gladiator types allowed a game's
organizer or editor to essentially make
any scenario he wanted. The only limit
to his imagination would be the scale of
the games at hand. But given the
magnitude of affairs in the coliseum,
almost anything was possible. Want to
make an epic rendition of the battle of
Marathon? He could do that. Want to make
an alternate history of Toyberg where
the Romans won? Totally possible. Want
to showcase the battle of Actium with
the heroic Romans pitted against the
dastardly rebels? No problem. Even with
real water and real boats. And yes,
naval gladiatorial combat was a real
thing, but we'll have to cover that in
another episode.
This should all give you a sense of the
pure entertainment value of these
spectacles. The fights tended to be like
modern pro wrestling with its colorful
characters, stage [music] conflicts, and
over-the-top production value. Of
course, with the added drama that this
was real blood and people could die.
Yet, even still, gladiatoral matches
were not as deadly as gets depicted in
modern media. After all, it took a lot
of time and effort to produce
gladiators, and killing off half of your
workforce every match was simply
unfeasible. Modern historians estimate
that 90% of duels actually ended with
both parties alive. This was made
possible by the fact that matches had
rules which would be enforced by a
referee in the ring. Groin shots, for
instance, would be barred, and the
fighters could be separated to their
corners for a refresher between rounds.
The gladiators themselves were
professionals who took an extreme amount
of pride in what they did. They put on a
good show, but were also careful of
where the limits were. For instance,
when a gladiator wanted to concede,
often before they were dealt crippling
damage, he would lift a finger to
indicate his surrender. Typically, this
meant the end of a match. However, if
the crowd disapproved of his
performance, they could shout, "Finish
him!" after which the gladiator was
expected to kneel before his opponent
who would stab him vertically at the
base of his neck, aiming for the heart.
One of the greatest identifiers of
gladiator graveyards is precisely this
particular brand of execution visible on
their remains. But for those who fought
bravely and did not meet such a grizzly
end, once out of the ring, everything
would be done to make sure that they
recovered to fight again. After all,
gladiators were a heavy business
investment, and it was in everyone's
best interest that they survived,
despite being involved in the world's
most famous blood sport. Gladiator
schools would therefore hire a permanent
doctor or surgeon on staff and had some
of the best medical care outside of the
legions themselves. Galen, Rome's most
famous doctor, had his beginnings in a
gladiator school, where he writes about
his use of antibiotics, wine or honey,
bandages, stitches, and medication. Even
the diet of the gladiator was tailored
to keep them alive. In Hollywood
depictions, gladiators are shown with
trim bodies and six-packs glistening in
the sun. In reality, though, gladiators
ate a diet that was almost exclusively
composed of broad bean and barley
porridge. It was exceptionally heavy on
both carbs and protein that coupled with
their incredibly demanding training
regimen gave them a heavy musculation
coupled with a significant layer of fat
that would act as a sort of natural
armor. They were trained to give shallow
wounds to each other. Wounds that would
bleed in a satisfying manner, but which
would generally not go through the outer
fat layer. In short, they were big men
whose looks more than matched their
reputation.
There will be much more to say about
gladiators, from their training to their
matches and the nature of the coliseum
itself. But for now, we hope you've
enjoyed this introduction to the rise of
the gladiators.
Gladiators step into the sands of the
arena and are greeted by the rockest
cheers of the crowds. They are athletes
of the highest caliber with the best
among them standing as celebrities known
far and wide. But this grand entrance
represented just a sliver of their lived
experience. How did one even become a
gladiator? How did they train? What did
they eat? How did they live? Today,
let's explore a day in the life of a
gladiator.
Gladiators to be came from all manner of
sources. These included slaves,
criminals, and even volunteers. There
was a vast industry in place for
sourcing such individuals from across
the Mediterranean and selling them off
to those who would eventually prepare
them for the arena. For much of Rome's
history, this would have been the task
of the gladiator schools or Ludy. Such
institutions were initially small
privatelyowned operations but eventually
became huge state-run enterprises. They
existed across the empire with an
understandable concentration being
located near major cities such as
Alexandria, Pergamum, and Capua. Rome
itself had four of these schools by the
first century AD with the largest of
these housing up to 2,000 men and the
Ludas Magnus being located right next to
the coliseum. Meanwhile, the remains of
a school at the site of Carnutum near
Vienna gives us a good idea of what
these would have looked like. The
complex is wrapped around a central
courtyard within which is an outdoor
training area and arena. The eastern
wing seems to contain the administrative
rooms and the owner's living quarters.
The southern wing features a gladiator
barracks with a row of 3x 7 m cell
blocks. The western wing also housed
gladiators, but was more luxuriously
built and thus is believed to have been
reserved for more high-ranking fighters.
And finally, the north wing provides
support facilities such as an assembly
hall, an indoor training room, and a
bath house. Beyond this complex are our
surrounding field, garden, and cemetery.
Typically, such schools were run by
Lannister, who was the manager and owner
of a gladiator troop or familia
gladiatoria. The poet Marshall indicates
that lower level lenasty were seen on
the same social footing as pimps.
Lenasty from the upper classes,
meanwhile, were [music] not so stained
and might even enjoy some level of
esteem from engaging in such a
profitable enterprise. Cicero, for
instance, congratulates his friend for
buying a splendid batch of gladiators
and notes that their cost would surely
be recovered after only two
performances.
So, now let's see what it was like for a
new gladiator to join such a school.
Upon arrival, we are told that it was
tradition for new members to swear a
gladiator's oath or sacramentum.
Petronius states, quote, "He vows to
endure to be burned, to be bound, to be
beaten, and to be killed by the sword."
For volunteers of the imperial era,
often looking to clear some debts, the
individual would also sign a contract,
Octura Tmentum, which dictated the terms
by which they willingly joined.
Thus, an individual became known as a
tiro, the same title as raw recruits
within the Roman legions. For both
inductees, they would now see a
reduction in their rights as they came
under a new disciplinary system. But
this was far harsher for gladiators, as
might be guessed from the language of
their oath. Those who joined became an
infamous. This would strip them of the
rights of Roman citizenship and included
various social and legal penalties.
Ultimately, their fate now lay in the
hands of the Lannista himself, acting as
head of the familia gladiatoria, who had
lawful power over the life and death of
all members of this family. In this way,
did even free volunteers become reduced
to the same social level as all others
who by one way or another entered the
gates of a gladiator school. However, we
should note that one's background did
still matter to some degree. For
example, those criminals condemned to
death at the games or dumnati at Ludum
were likely branded or tattooed and face
quite severe treatment. But they weren't
the only ones to be singled out. Soon
the rest of their comrades would also be
segregated into the school's rigid
hierarchy. As juvenile remarks, quote,
"Even the lowest scum of the arena
observe this rule. Even in prison,
they're separate."
This process would occur over the course
of one's training. It started as the new
Tro gladiators were subjected to an
initial period of inspection to assess
their physical and mental
characteristics. Both would factor into
determining what type of gladiator a
recruit would become. This was important
as each specialization had a distinct
way of being equipped, trained, and used
in the arena. Another factor in such
decisions would be recruits background.
After all, a good story could do wonders
for spicing up a gladiatorial match.
Thus, Alanista might buy a young Thrian
slave and train them to fight in the
caricaturured manner of their homeland.
Once their combat style was determined,
a tiro would be assigned to the care of
a specific trainer known in Latin as the
dotores or the magistrate. Each had
their own area of expertise, such as the
doctor Mumulonum, the doctorum, or the
doctor. Likely such skilled specialists
were at one point gladiators themselves.
Once within the care of a trainer, a new
gladiator would now begin to ascend
through a hierarchy of grades. This
began at the level of the novice or
Novaki and went all the way up to the
highest grades of Primis polace. The
better the fighter, the higher the price
Alanista could fetch for their matches.
This in turn trickled down to the
gladiator as moving up the ranks
resulted in progressively higher pay and
improved treatment. To give you context,
I will now provide an example of what
this sort of progression might look
like. The novice would begin with the
basics. Here they were drilled
physically on exercise routines, on
stances, and on weapon handling. The
latter was likely carried out with
blunted or wood inversions against a
training pole. At the same time, they
were also mentally drilled on the
discipline and stoicism necessary to
live the life of a gladiator. While some
of the condemned criminals might be
thrown into the arena at this point as
cannon fodder, most would likely have
received a bit more training before
setting foot before a crowd. After all,
gladiatorial matches were a form of
entertainment, and the masses were
rarely satisfied with a fighter who
looked like they could be blown over by
the wind.
Thus, at the lower ranks, a gladiator
would begin to master the fundamental
rules and customs of fighting in the
arena. The goal would have been to have
them be able to execute the basic
motions necessary to at least put up a
fight. It wasn't pretty, but at least
they would survive to earn more money
for their Lannista. Thus, the metrics
for success at this level was probably
to aim for more yawns than booze. A
great example of how audiences perceive
this type of match comes from
Petronius's satiricon. Here, a character
complaints loudly at the poor quality of
a gladiator troop with the exception of
a Thrax. Though he grumbles that even
this man fought Adictata, or according
to his lessons,
the next ranks of training were probably
geared towards satisfying this type of
viewer. Gladiators further specialized
and could begin to reliably put on a
show. This meant fighting in even larger
arenas at the more coveted time slots.
Once having gained some reputation in
this manner, Elanista might find
additional ways to monetize the
beginnings of fame by loaning them out
for private events as fighters, guards,
or prostitutes.
At the highest levels, the performance
of a primis polace would be preserved
for the climax of a show and could be
expected to draw in huge crowds in the
way that headliners do today. These men
were celebrities in their own right who
brought in a lot of money for their
managers. Thus, they were well taken
care of and enjoyed many benefits. This
included accumulating significant wealth
with which to even begin supporting a
family or work their way towards
freedom. The exact details of a
gladiator's career could certainly vary
wildly, but hopefully this gives you a
general idea of what training look like.
Now, let's begin to explore the other
aspects of their daily life.
The world of a gladiator would mostly
have been restricted to the confines of
the Lutus. Here they stuck to a
regimented schedule. Each day began
within the barracks alongside the rest
of the men of their troop. They awoke
inside a small cell. Records reveal
these were laconic to say the least. But
such accommodations were likely
decorated with a few personal
belongings, at least as much as the
guards would allow. Exceptions, of
course, could be made for those who
earned the Lennis's favor.
Next, the gladiators would be released
from captivity for a morning meal in the
messaul. Ancient sources described the
unique aspects of a gladiator's diet.
Rather than resting upon the foundation
of wheat bread like the rest of the
population, it instead relied upon
barley. This earned them the nickname
hiari or eaters of barley. Such rations
were looked down upon by the general
public as fodder for animals and were
even issued as punishment to soldiers
for dishonorable behavior. However, when
prepared as a porridge, it was at least
palatable. The ancient doctor Galen
describes the specific recipe used by
gladiators as calling for the barley to
be soaked, husked, and boiled. To this
bowl was added cooked faba beans and
slices of dried fruit such as apples.
Nutritionally, it was packed with
protein and carbs. But a final key
ingredient was the addition of ash. This
helped provide a much needed source of
calcium. Indeed, an analysis of
gladiator skeletons reveals remarkably
developed bone structures when compared
to the average person of the period.
This diet would provide the fuel needed
to maintain their active lifestyle and
over time help them gain the fleshy
layers of fat best suited for a natural
armor that would bleed well but
relatively harmlessly when slashed in
the arena.
Next, the gladiators would join their
trainers for drills within the practice
grounds of the complex. It is here that
they would carry out much of the
training we previously described. A
large part of this would have involved
practicing moves against wooden posts or
sparring with opponents in what was
referred to as the Armatura.
This would also have been an opportunity
for the Lannista to observe how his
investments were developing.
But the day's grueling training schedule
would certainly have taken a toll on
gladiators. The presence of bath
complexes indicates that this was
anticipated.
Thus, we must imagine that part of an
athletes routine would have involved
receiving regular massages and soaking
in tubs to melt away at least some of
the pain. For more serious injuries and
concerns of long-term care, however,
they might stop by the school's doctor.
Records indicate that Gladiator schools
actually had some of the best medical
care outside of the army. The famed
Greek physician Galen actually received
much of his training from the Ludist in
Pergamum. It was from these experiences
that he wrote the following commentary
regarding the health of athletes.
Quote, we've been considering the
greatest good of the body, that is
health. Let us turn to other bodily
goods. As regards beauty, athletics is
very far from contributing to it.
Indeed, men have frequently started off
with very well-proportioned bodies, been
taken by athletic trainers, fattened
excessively and filled with blood and
flesh, and ended up in quite the
opposite state.
You may say that bodily pleasure is a
good, but they do not enjoy this either.
Not while they are training certainly,
nor afterwards. During their athletic
activity, they are all in miserable
pain, whether from their exercise or
from the enforced eating. When they
stop, most parts of their bodies become
deformed. He goes on to speak at length
about the precarious state of
maintaining their peak condition and
how, like city walls which have
withstood a siege, the body can come
crashing down from sustained pressure.
Thus, it was that a prudent Lannister
would cut his gladiators some slack
rather than grinding them down to the
point of collapse. It was in these
moments of downtime that they might be
able to socialize with their peers. This
allowed them to not only blow off steam,
but also to form important support
groups. After all, the life of a
gladiator took just as heavy a toll on
the mind as it did the body.
Understandably, we hear of many
references to depression and suicide
among gladiators. Through it all, one's
familia would be there to share in these
struggles of daily life. But the daily
routine we have just described would
occasionally be broken up by off-campus
trips. Here, gladiators might take part
in all manner of activities. This was
often in service of the Lannist's
agenda, such as being rented out for
private use. In the run-up to an arena
match, they might even be put on display
as a way to promote the games.
Apparently, the night before a fight,
gladiators would be treated to an
elaborate meal. This was a small silver
lining to what must have otherwise been
a quite nerve-inducing time. Indeed,
Plutarch describes that even at their
most lavish banquetss, quote, "The night
before they enter the arena, when many
expensive and lavish dishes are laid
before them, they find greater pleasure
in asking their friends to care for
their women and freeing their slaves
than they do in gratifying their
bellies.
Eventually, when the day came,
gladiators would be brought into the
arena. This began with a triumphal
parade which kicked off such events. As
they entered from the gates, the crowds
would go wild. For first timers and even
veterans, the rush of adrenaline must
have been incredible. While the famous
line, "We who are about to die salute
you," was not actually a common refrain,
it is certain that all men who entered
the arena did so with the understanding
that death was with them in the sands.
However, contrary to popular belief,
most gladiator matches did not end in
death. After all, there were referees
and rules for submission. So long as a
good show was made, both sides stood a
good chance of walking away with their
lives. Gladiators, as we have seen, were
a huge investment, and it was in the
best interest of Alanista to train them
to return home to fight again. Those who
did would receive a hero's welcome.
However, it was always a somber moment
to learn that one's friend was not among
the living.
This was just one more of the dreadful
tolls of a gladiator's life. The
veterans who made it through many years
of service would have long become numb
to such moments and adopted a stoic
outlook on life. But a glimmer of hope
could be had that one day, through this
gauntlet of suffering, they might
eventually attain freedom. For some,
this meant rising through the ranks high
enough to be given some personal and
financial liberties with which to enjoy
life. Others, meanwhile, might even gain
full emancipation after a long career or
a particularly noteworthy victory. But
it seems that even those who escaped the
confines of the Lutus could rarely
escape the gravitational pull of the
industry. Many veterans went on to
become trainers who raised the next
generation of fighters. And thus, the
cycle of the gladiator life continued.
The ancient crowds of the Roman arena
always hungered for new forms of
entertainment. This desire could only be
sated by the hosting of ever more
massive games involving hundreds of
fighters and elaborately staged
productions. It's in this entertainment
arms race that such novelties as the
famed Namakia were developed.
Today though, let us focus on another
one of these exotic displays, the female
gladiators of the arena.
Records of gladiator combat permeate the
majority of Roman history, even going as
far back as the Atruscans. As the
centuries wore on, and as the
politicians of the Roman Republic looked
to distinguish themselves more and more,
the great games and festivals known as
Mona became increasingly elaborate.
After all, there was no better way to
make a name for yourself than through
this most exciting of advertising
platforms. And so it was that the most
ambitious men of their age sought power
through the bread and circuses of the
games.
In these matters, there were two major
factors to making a series of great
distinct games. An editor could either
go big or go unique.
Size could be the number of gladiators,
parades, or condemn criminals with
bragging statements on the numbers of
these appearing in both pre and postgame
inscriptions.
Uniqueness, on the other hand, was by
far the more alluring trait. This could
be achieved by bringing animals in from
beyond Rome's borders, as well as
through unique displays such as dressing
your gladiators in pure silver or by
using distinctive acts. Today, we're
covering perhaps one of the most
evocative of these acts, the gladiatrix.
The word gladiatrix is not attested in
ancient literature and is in fact a
modern distinction. Latin inscriptions
and references describe quote women
fighting in the arena or quote women
wielding swords. But for our purposes,
it's much more convenient to use the
word gladiatrix in a similar fashion to
the way we might refer to the Eastern
Roman Empire simply as the Byzantines.
Sourcing on gladiatrices is generally
pretty rare since the vast majority of
gladiators were men trained in all male
schools. The idea of women fighting was
scandalous to the Romans and so
predictably this meant that gladies were
incredibly popular in their events, even
if those events were probably pretty
rare. Emperors looking to make their
games distinct would advertise massive
games at which female gladiators were
prominent. More minor officials would
also advertise gladiatores as the
memorable event at their games,
memorialized in inscriptions such as
this hyperbolic claim that states,
quote, "Hastilianis was the first of
everyone since the founding of the city
to hold games with gladiators as well as
giving women the sword." Needless to
say, that inscription, which dates to
the late 2nd century AD, is blatantly
hyperbolic. Not only is the man in
question not the first to hold games
with gladiators and swords women, but
he's also not the first person to allow
women into the arena to fight. That
distinction actually goes back to the
murky and confusing days of the early
imperial era, the age of Augustus.
Augustus is actually well known as a
relatively prudish emperor putting laws
in place in an attempt to return Rome to
the good old days. This included a
number of incentives for the traditional
family, the number of children every
family should have, and the role of
women in society. It's here that we
actually have one of our more
fascinating surviving pieces of imperial
legislation. The inscription etched in
bronze declares the following. Quote,
"No one should bring to the arena a
senator's son, daughter, grandson,
granddaughter, great-grandson,
great-granddaughter, or any male whose
father or grandfather, whether paternal
or maternal, or brother, or any female
whose husband or father or grandfather,
whether paternal or maternal or brother,
had ever possessed the right of sitting
in the seats reserved for the
equestrians, or induced them by means of
a fee to appear, or to snatch the plumes
of gladiators, or take the training
sword from anyone, or to take part in
any way in any similar subordinate
capacity. While this ban applied just as
much to theater as it did to the arena,
it's telling in its specificity, namely
in targeting of the youth. Here we see
how the Roman old guard was deeply upset
by the young men and women who
participated in acts that they found
shameful. This situation was absolutely
unacceptable to the Romans. Being a
performer in any capacity was actually
thought to bring on a concept called
infamia. Strictly speaking, it was the
loss of legal or social standing. But
like any Roman concept, it's a bit
difficult to put that word into English.
Mere dishonor doesn't do it justice. And
Famia was more like a black spot on
one's very soul that could easily spread
throughout the entire family. After all,
if someone of that bloodline could be
brought so low, then anyone else surely
could as well.
Gladiators and gladiatrices were in the
same category as anyone else who sold
their bodies for money, such as actors
and even prostitutes. For a woman to
take up a sword on top of that might
well be entertaining for all viewers,
but that was rooted in the fact that
that entertainment was pure shock value
for the Romans who looked on. Augustus'
law gives us a clue that the first signs
of gladiatores were probably in the
early empire and was probably an
extension of women appearing
increasingly on stage at the theater.
After all, male gladiators were
basically just actors using live
weapons. So why would it be the case
that women were not doing the same?
If they did take up arms, then they were
probably trained in private traveling
schools in a similar fashion to actors.
These [snorts] would have been able to
offer their services at a premium far
and wide. While we have written records
of repeated appearances in the city of
Rome, the only surviving engraving that
clearly depicts two female gladiators is
in Helarnaces, a city in southwestern
Anatolia.
These two gladitrices were named Amazon
and Echela for this contest, probably in
a recreation of the fame combat between
Achilles and the queen of the Amazon.
While Achilles prevailed in the herriic
version, this genderbent live action
scene apparently ended in a draw.
Perhaps what's most interesting is that
women in the scene are dressed exactly
the same way as their male counterparts.
They were bare-chested, dressed in heavy
but revealing gear. And one of them even
holds her sword in her left hand, a
popular stance for gladiators to throw
their opponent off guard.
Gladiatrices probably fought with the
same rules as the gladiators themselves.
They were heavily trained to maintain
their discipline and concentration.
After all, theirs was a blood sport, and
they were not necessarily expected to
fight to the death. Gladiatoral combats
were a show for entertainment more than
anything else, and the gladiatores were
no exception. They would fight and bleed
in a showy manner, but there was always
a referee to break them up if one seemed
to be losing her head.
In preparation for these fights, they
would certainly exercise hard, though
it's difficult to tell whether their
regimen was the same as the male
gladiators in the more permanent
schools. Nonetheless, they probably
maintained a similar diet of faba bean
porridge and charcoal water.
Professional doctors too were maintained
by all gladiator troops and gladiatrices
would probably have merited
top-of-the-line doctors as well. After
all, they were considered to be an
exotic rare commodity. That rarity would
have merited higher prices, and thus
those prices would have encouraged their
owner to keep them at peak performance.
Some of the first major records of women
fighting in the arena was done about the
reign of Nero. While some of these
accounts are certainly exaggerated, we
do know that he was infamous for loving
gladiatorial displays to an unhealthy
degree. The first of these displays was
apparently held during the games in
memory of his mother when Nero
apparently held a full retelling of
Roman history on the sands with the
families of the famous. Here's how one
of our sources puts it. Quote, "In honor
of his mother, he celebrated a most
magnificent and costly festival. The
events taking place for several days in
five or six theaters at once. It was on
this occasion that an elephant was led
to the highest gallery of the theater
and walked down from that point on ropes
carrying a rider. There was also another
exhibition that was at once most
disgraceful and most shocking when men
and women not only of the equestrian but
even of the senatorial order appeared as
performers in the orchestra, in the
circus and in the hunting theater like
those who are held in lowest esteem.
Some of them played the flute and danced
in pantoimes or acted in tragedies and
comedies or sang to the liar. They drove
horses, killed wild beasts, and fought
as gladiators, some willingly and some
very much against their will.
In telling these stories, Cashas Dio was
doing his best to paint Nero in the
worst light possible. But this kind of
display does seem plausible for a man
who happily indulged himself in his
pursuits of the arts. His further
descriptions, such as the implication
that male and female gladiators were
paired off to have sex in the arena, are
a bit more suspect, but even then aren't
entirely unbelievable. As I mentioned
earlier, gladiators were seen as
performers in every aspect, selling
their bodies for the pleasure of the
crowd. A scenario straight out of a porn
movie wouldn't be too terrifically out
of place, albeit distasteful for the
Roman aristocracy.
But Nero didn't stop there. It seems
that Gladiatores enjoyed a relatively
regular amount of time on the sands. One
future incident, which Cash's Dio refers
to as a disgrace, involved a visit from
the Parthion king and his family. Nero
lavished them with unimaginable wealth
at every instant of their journey,
allotting them 800,000 sisters per day
for the nine months of their journey.
Nero met the foreign king at Neopoulos
the moment that he landed in Italy, and
they both traveled from there to Rome.
Quote, Nero threw him a gladiatoral
exhibition at Putoli. It was under the
direction of Petrobius, one of his
breeder men, who managed to make it a
most brilliant and costly affair, as may
be seen from the fact that on one of the
days, Ethiopians, men, women, and
children, were the only ones who
appeared in the arena. It's unclear
exactly what story was attempting to be
told here, but perhaps it may have been
the story of Andromeda, but at the same
time, we know that Ethiopians in general
were significantly less likely to have
been enslaved by the Romans, who had
never conquered the region. It's far
more likely that these performers were
recruited specifically for this
exhibition, likely making it far more
expensive in many ways, but also
highlighting Nero's love of seeing women
in performing roles.
Interestingly, one of Rome's poets of
the Twitter troll variety makes several
illusions to gladrices in the first
century AD. Oftentimes, he includes
these illusions in his costic mockery of
Rome's supposedly effeminite culture,
where men were apparently just as likely
to sleep with men as they were to sleep
with women. He notes one particular
woman who may or may not be real named
Mevia who was famous for her
bare-chested performances during the
arena beast hunts. Even he notes though
that there aren't many women wrestlers
or women on an athletes diet.
Looking through our records, it appears
that ancient historians mostly seem to
ignore when these spectacles took place
unless they could be used as a sign that
the emperor in question was a negative
influence on society. Dimmission, for
instance, was known for not only
allowing women to participate in foot
races among men, but also was especially
fond of glades and held regular matches
with them, pitting them against each
other in stage combat. Cashas Dio and
Sutonius both note this with disgust, as
well as emphatically highlighting that
some of these games were even held at
night by torch light. While there's no
explicit record of it, there's also a
distinct possibility that some of these
gladiatories may have participated in
dimmissions Namakia. In contrast to some
of the more negative historians, a
fawning account written by a poet who is
not trying to get himself killed tells
of these women in the arena taking
position on either side, fighting like
the Amazon. It's unclear though if these
were attempting to act out stories of
the Amazon or if it was just a poetic
device by this author.
In heavy contrast to all this is the
treatment of Titus, the mission's older
brother. Titus essentially gets a free
pass from ancient historians in that he
died only 2 years after he ascended to
the throne. As a result, he's known for
two main things while on the throne. His
response to the eruption of Vuvius and
the inauguration of the Flavian
Amphitheater, also known as the Roman
coliseum. Multiple sources attest to the
fact that women participated in these
inaugural events, though it's not
explicitly clear if they performed as
glades or just in the beast hunts.
Marshall references that the emperor,
not satisfied with Mars alone, also
brought Venus in to delight the crowds.
The theme of this spectacle was to stage
a retelling of the myth. So there was
one criminal woman who played the role
of pacifi raped to death by a bull. A
man played Prometheus and was gored by
animals while strapped to a cross.
Heracles was also apparently gender bent
and the unnamed gladrix won rapturous
applause for killing the Nian lion.
Unlike the more corrupt emperors, Titus
actually won commentary and some praise
for this. He notably made sure to use
only lower-ass women, which made it a
little bit more palatable for later
historians and the Roman upper classes.
Regardless, gladiatores continue to be a
popular, if rare attraction throughout
the first century AD. They were seen as
novelties throughout. And while sources
are essentially non-existent, it can be
generally assumed that a similar
sentiment prevailed through the 2nd
century as well. One of the only
surviving sources from this time period
is the aforementioned inscription in
Austia by Hostilian claiming that he was
the first person to ever bring warrior
women into the arena. Additionally,
there's a skeleton that was found
outside London that may be the body of a
female gladiator, as evidenced by the
fact that she was buried with a number
of honorific items, including a lamp
that was emblased with a triumphal
gladiatoral match. Her bones, though,
are generally free of the damage that
gladiators endured, so it's impossible
to truly say what she was involved in.
The assumed end of the era of the
gladrixes came with Zeptimius Seis.
Around the year 200, it seems he held a
massive athletics competition with
people from across the empire. Here,
women were included, competing with each
other in the same types of events as the
men, but the Roman audience was filled
with as many cat calls as cheers. Many
of these cat calls were directed at
aristocratic women asking why they were
so demir when the athletes were fiery
and passionate. Details are
frustratingly scarce about the event,
but Cash's Dio tarsely claims that
quote, "Therefore, it was henceforth
forbidden for any women, no matter what
her origin, to fight in single combat."
From this point on, it seems that female
gladiators were barred entirely. While
it's possible that some instances may
have occurred, especially after the
death of Septimius Seis, there are no
sources to support this, and therefore,
we must assume that this held from now
on until the end of the Roman era.
The gladiatoral games of ancient Rome
were spectacles we today can barely
imagine. While modern media certainly
made a valid attempt, these only reveal
the tip of the iceberg. For instance,
they failed to capture the sheer
enormity of men, animals, and elaborate
props which filled the fighting pits for
days, weeks, and even months on end.
Worse yet, they somehow completely
ignore the naval battles fought in the
coliseum and in the massive artificial
lakes, which reportedly featured tens of
thousands of combatants and upwards of
100 ships. Today, let us explore the
fascinating and often overlooked world
of Rome's Namaki.
Gladiatorial combat had its humble
beginnings in theerary games practiced
by the elites of the early Roman
Republic. Here games were private
religious events which featured just a
handful of fighters who clashed over a
matter of minutes. But as soon as word
got out, the tanalyzing nature of this
blood sport quickly drew an audience.
The populace had a new form of
entertainment and the politicians had a
new form of propaganda. Thus, gladiators
were now catapulted to the forefront of
the Roman world. At every turn, event
organizers now dreamed up new ways to
wow the crowds and outdo their
competitors with ever more extravagant
spectacles. By the late Republic, this
meant having hundreds of duelists and
exotic animals fighting it out amidst
elaborately decorated stages over the
course of days, weeks, and even months.
It is during this era that a young
Julius Caesar would first make a name
for himself, not on the battlefield, but
in the arena. For instance, as Edall in
65 BC, he organized games on such an
unprecedented scale and expense that it
would skyrocket his career. But he
didn't just stop there. The
entrepreneurial showman soon pioneered
new ways to outperform his rivals by
bringing the games to a whole new
dimension, the sea. This ambitious plan
to host the first ever Namakia would be
unveiled for the celebration of his
quadruple triumph in the year 46 BC.
This of course was a monumental task.
Caesar wished to bring the full
spectacle of naval battles to the people
of Rome. No expense was to be spared.
For example, rather than relying on
miniature or prop vessels, his plans
called for the use of actual full-scale
warships. Such brooms, triams, and
quariums could be as long as 45 m and
required even more space to effectively
maneuver. Thus, their arena would have
to be even larger than this. The natural
choice would have been to simply let the
ships fight it out at sea. However, the
shore lay around 25 km from the city and
would have been relatively inaccessible
to the majority of the population.
Something closer to home would have to
do. Unfortunately, the coliseum had not
yet been built and the only existing
facilities that might be large enough to
hold such an event would be the Circus
Maximus. Yet, it did not have the
necessary features to accommodate
flooding and was likely being reserved
for other events. Ultimately then it was
decided that a brand new facility would
be built next to it in the field of Mars
adjacent to the Tyber from which it drew
its water. Sutonius describes the scene.
Quote, "For the naval battle, a pool was
dug in the lesser conda and there was a
contest of ships of two, three, and four
banks of oars representing the Tyrion
and Egyptian fleets manned by a large
force of fighting men. Such a throng
flocked to all these shows from every
quarter that many strangers had to lodge
in tents pitched in streets or along the
roads. And the press was often such that
many were crushed to death, including
two senators.
We can only imagine the insanity of such
an event that reportedly featured some
2,000 combatants and 4,000 rowers
staffed by prisoners of war. These were
disposable forces meant to be smashed
against one another for the
entertainment of the crowds.
Thus, as cheers echoed across the
waters, the trapped victims were left to
fight for their lives in what became a
very real battle where ships rammed,
boarded, and shot each other to pieces.
The event unquestionably set a new
benchmark for the pinnacle of Roman
entertainment. Yet, despite its apparent
success, the new naval arena would
quickly fall into disrepair as the
Republic once again fell into civil war
following the assassination of Julius
Caesar. Its memory, though, would
endure. When Augustus emerged as the
ultimate master of Rome, he would
finally bring back stability to a
battered realm. Much of this involved
new building projects to push imperial
propaganda, glorifying his victories and
appeasing the people. Among these would
be the construction of a temple to Mars
the Avenger. Finally inaugurated in 2
BC, it would be a great monument which
was to house the legendary eagles of
Cassus which had recently been recovered
from the Parththeians. In commemoration
of this event, Augustus would revise the
Namaki with a planned reenactment of a
naval battle between the Greeks and the
Persians. But rather than attempt to
reuse the now drained and dilapitated
remains of Caesar's naval arena,
Augustus had a new basin dug along the
Tyber with an island in the center for
VIP seating. The details are recounted
in his autobiography.
Quote, I gave the people a spectacle of
a naval battle in the place across the
Tyber, digging 1,800 ft in length and
1,200 in width in which 30 beak ships,
brooms or triams, but many smaller
fought among themselves. About 3,000 men
fought in these ships in addition to the
rowers.
Once again, we are left to imagine the
sheer spectacle of this event, which
appears to have been even grander than
that of Caesar some 40 years earlier.
Not only were there more reported
combatants, but the infrastructure
behind the entire project was more
impressive. For instance, the later
Roman engineer Frontius describes how an
entire aqueduct was built to fill the
naval arena at a moment's notice. This
Aqua Austa found its source in the
Alcatina Lake in Aturia and ran over 30
km to the city of Rome. Here, its
non-portable water could be diverted
into nearby gardens, fountains, and
irrigation works were not needed for the
Namakia. Over the years, this basin and
the surrounding area would come to be
known as the Grove of the Caesars. While
naval games could still be held there,
it slowly transformed into a popular
leisure spot. The vast gardens provided
refuge from the hub of the city and soon
attracted a regular crowd. These, in
turn, drew in numerous merchants and
vendors who began to set up shop along
its outskirts. Naturally, a large number
of brothel were also set up with
prostitutes now becoming as common as
the geese which made their home upon the
artificial lake.
The next major Namakia would again take
place roughly 50 years after its
predecessor. It was hosted in 52 AD by
the emperor Claudius in commemoration of
a great drainage project set to begin
regulating the levels of the Great
Faulen Lake. This engineering marvel was
the product of a decade's worth of labor
by some 30,000 workers and was well
worth celebrating. Thus, it was decided
that the naval games would be set upon
the lake itself. This had the advantage
of vastly increasing the scope of the
Namakia since the Faulian lake is
estimated to have had a surface area of
around 120 km. Thus unshackled by space
limitations, Claudius was said to have
deployed 100 ships and 19,000 combatants
for his games in an attempt to recreate
combat between Sicilian and Rodian
forces. If these numbers are even
remotely true, then the Mach fleets
would have dwarfed most actual combat
fleets of the era. Tacitus sets the
scene as follows. Quote, Claudius lined
the circumference of the lake with rafts
that there might be no means of escape
at various points, but he still left
full space for the strength of the
crews, the skill of the pilots, the
impact of the vessels, and the usual
operations of a sea fight. On the rafts
stood companies of the Ptorian cohorts
and cavalry with the breast work in
front of them from which catapults and
ballistas might be worked. The rest of
the lake was occupied by marines on
decked vessels. An immense multitude
from the neighboring towns, others from
Rome itself, eager to see the site or to
show respect of the emperor, crowded the
banks, the hills, the mountaintops,
which thus resembled a theater. The
emperor, meanwhile, with Agraina seated
near him, presided. He wore a splendid
military cloak. She, a mantle of cloth
of gold.
The criminal gladiators, forced to staff
the ships, and now surrounded by an
entire army, likely had a pretty good
idea of the fate which awaited them. It
is thus understandable why they are
reported to have raised their swords to
the emperor with the famous line, "Hail
Caesar, we who are about to die salute
you." Such an extreme declaration is not
reported in any other games, and for
good reason. The gladiatorial land
battles were often fought between
expensive professionals meant to put on
highly performative shows with
relatively low mortality rates.
Gladiatorial naval battles, on the other
hand, appear to have been staffed by
cheap criminals whom the Romans had no
qualms about killing. Thus, combat
itself was wildly unregulated with no
referees to separate combatants between
bouts and no real way to surrender or
retreat. Even if your ship did manage to
win or evade boarding action, it could
at any moment be rammed from the side
and sunk to the bottom of the lake with
survivors unable to swim or escape the
carnage around them.
Great anticipation must therefore have
swept through the crowds of spectators
who lined the stands and surrounding
hills awaiting the main event of the
day. Finally, the warm-up acts of
theater groups and pontoon fighters were
concluded and the real battle could
commence. Sutonius tells us that this
was marked by the blowing of a silver
horn from the middle of the lake.
However, to the dismay of the Romans, it
seems that the participants were none
too eager to charge to their own death
and remained in place. As a result,
Tacitus mentions that Imperial guards on
rafts were sent out to force the two
sides to engage. Yet, even when these
did advance, they harmlessly sailed past
one another. At this point, the crowd
must have begun to boo at such boring
cowardice. Dash's Dio reports that the
emperor remedied this situation by
forcing the gladiator fleets to
continuously repeat their maneuvers
until they inevitably destroyed one
another. Finally, Tacitus tells us the
fleets engaged with a great fighting
spirit. Undoubtedly, this was a
spectacle of epic proportions met with
the rockous cheers of the crowd.
In the years ahead, such fervor would
only increase as the golden age of the
gladiators ensured that Namakia appeared
in ever greater frequencies.
We next hear of additional Namaki during
the reign of Claudius's successor, Nero.
He was certainly an extravagant emperor
and there should be no surprise when
this attitude manifested in the form of
additional naval games. We are told for
instance that these were hosted on two
occasions in 57 and 64 AD within a newly
constructed wooden amphitheater built on
the campus marshes close to where Julius
Caesar had hosted the first such games.
While the artificial nature of this
event meant that it was smaller than
that of Claudius, the controlled
environment allowed for far more
flexibility and diversity in the way the
entertainment played out. Here is how
Cash's Dio describes it. Quote, "In the
course of producing a spectacle at one
of the theaters, he suddenly filled the
place with seaater so that fishes and
sea monsters swam about in it, and he
exhibited a naval battle between men
representing the Persians and Athenians.
After this, he immediately drew off the
water, dried the ground, and once more
exhibited contests between land forces
who fought not only in single combat,
but also in large groups equally
matched.
Unfortunately, it seems that these
facilities were even shorter lived than
Nero and appear to have been lost in the
great fire of Rome, which racked the
city in 64 AD. The civil war, which
followed shortly thereafter, further
stymied any attempts at holding naval
games. However, when peace once again
returned under the new Flavian dynasty,
there would be a chance to build back
better than ever before. The prime
example of this would be the
construction of the brand new coliseum,
starting in 70 AD under Vespasian and
completing in 80 AD under Titus.
Evidence suggests that it was
purpose-built to host both land and
naval gladiator battles. Though the
exact engineering details are somewhat
elusive, we can share some basic points
regarding its construction.
The first point to be made is that the
site of the coliseum had actually once
been its own artificial lake. This was
drained, excavated, and a deep
foundation set. At the center of it all
was left the pit of the arena roughly 6
m deep. Its initial design called for
land-based fighting to take place at the
bottom of this cavity with the more
extensive gallery seen today being added
at a later date. Thus, with the basement
or hippo gym of the coliseum essentially
empty, it would have served as the
perfect bathtub for naval battles. This
was made possible by the fact that the
hippogy was lined with tightly packed
stone [music] and waterproof mortar.
Based on the fact that service galleries
were set at about 1.5 m above the
basement floor, researchers believe that
this was the intended flood depth for
the coliseum. Using some rough math,
that means it was engineered to hold
about 17,000 cubic meters of water. But
where exactly did all of this water come
from? And where did it all go?
The answer lies with the extensive
plumbing which was built into the
coliseum. Water, for instance, primarily
came from the 70 km long Aqua Claudia
aqueduct. A branch of it had previously
been used to feed the artificial lake of
Nero and is believed to have been
similarly plugged into the coliseum.
This appears to have been done by way of
around 30 to 40 conduits which have been
found leading into the pit of the arena.
At the time of their construction, these
would have contained lead pipes for
suitable water control. The Roman
engineer Frontius tells us that the Aqua
Claudia had a volutric flow of 2.12 m/s.
Assuming a full diversion of this flow,
it would therefore have taken about 2 to
three hours to fill the hippoim.
To assist in the process and to
alleviate the shutdown of other water
services, some researchers believed that
a nearby sistern was available for the
emergency infusion of water. Not only
could this have helped speed up the
process, but it also could have helped
supply the numerous fountains and
misters meant to keep the crowds cool
and hydrated.
As for draining the coliseum, we have
evidence of four large sewers which
leave the structure along its radial
axes. These were more than capable of
draining the hippogimum of its 17,000
cubic meter contents as well as its more
regular bouts of rain water and other
waste. All of it was carried away into
the city's main sewage system, which in
turn made its way out to the Tyber and
the surrounding countryside. The process
of draining the coliseum was likely
faster than filling it and was probably
accomplished in an hour or less.
Once all of this intricate plumbing and
infrastructure had been put in place,
the rest of the coliseum was slowly
built up to accommodate the crowds of
Rome. This would finally be completed in
80 AD, at which point enormous games
were set to be held to commemorate this
achievement. We are told that these
lasted 100 days, featuring hundreds of
fighters and thousands of wild animals.
Here, the Namaki made their glorious
return with one being held in the basin
of Augustus and another being held in
the coliseum itself. Cashas Du reports
the following quote for Titus suddenly
filled the same theater with water and
brought in horses and bulls and some
other domesticated animals that had been
taught to behave in the liquid element
just as on land. He also brought in
people on ships who engaged in a sea
fight there impersonating the Corkans
and Corinthians and others gave a
similar exhibition outside the city in
the grove of gas and Lucius a place
where Augustus had once excavated for
this very purpose.
Both experiences must have been distinct
in their own way. The Namakia of the
Augustine Basin appears to have featured
several thousand fighters with full-size
ships performing actual maneuvers as had
occurred in the earlier naval fights of
the Julio Claudians. The Namakia of the
Colosseum, meanwhile, was far more
constricted, likely featuring just a
handful of boats which were not at full
size or capable of much maneuvering.
Nonetheless, these still had all the
advantages of the arena's attention to
detail with various stage props of
rocks, shipwrecks, and islands being
used to up the level of entertainment.
The next emperor, dimmission, further
invested in the coliseum, adding a
fourth level, additional seating, and
new galleries in the basement. Namaki
were once again held in the coliseum in
85 AD, but perhaps owing to the
complications of new construction were
then moved to a new basin dug along the
Tyber for the Namakia of 89 AD. Here Dio
recounts that quote there was a naval
battle between 3,000 men followed by an
infantry battle. The Athenians conquered
the Syracusans, made a landing on the
island, and assaulted and captured a
wall that had been constructed around
the monument.
Based on this description, it seems that
this was a return to form for the grand
outdoor spectacles of old. However, we
should also mention that this was the
beginning of the end for the naval
gladiator games. Few sources make
mention of Namaki beyond the Flavian
period with the notable exception of
Trajan, who was said to have built a new
basin with bleachers to the northwest of
the Tyber. It was reportedly just 16th
the size of the Augustine basin and only
capable of hosting rather small games.
This speaks to the overall decline of
the Namaki, which appear to have begun
to have lost their novelty and grandeur.
Over the years, it is assumed that
various naval games continued to be held
outside of our written records, but that
eventually these would simply peter out
with the end of the golden age of the
gladiators.
Nonetheless, their legacy would live on
among the provincial theaters which
hosted their own namaki as well as among
the powers of the medieval era and
beyond who also celebrated their own
mock naval battles.
We hope you've appreciated this foray
into the untouched world of naval
gladiator battles. It's a fascinating
spectacle to imagine, especially when
you begin to consider the insane works
of logistics and engineering which went
into making them a reality. What are
your thoughts on the matter? And if you
could choose, which of the great land or
naval battles would you have liked to
witness at the time?
The Romans had many sources of
entertainment, but none loom so large
for them or even us today as the fame
spectacles in the coliseum. Yet, while
most media focus their attention on what
happened within the bloodstained arena,
today I wanted to explore what it would
be like from the perspective of your
everyday spectator. All the way from
buying your ticket to finding your seat,
getting snacks, rooting for your
favorite gladiator, winning prizes, and
rushing home to beat the traffic. So,
come on, let's spend a day at the games.
I wanted to begin by setting the
historical stage for you. After all,
gladiatoral games were an old Roman
tradition which stretched out and
evolved over roughly 800 years. We cover
this history in greater depth in our
episode on the rise of the gladiators
which you can check out. But for now, I
will provide just a brief overview. The
basic idea is that the blood sport began
as a religious ritual meant to honor the
dead. Such mona were initially privately
held but gradually came to take place in
public spaces. Here they quickly
attracted an audience as the
entertainment and propaganda value of
these events proved self-evident.
Soon politicians began to compete
fiercely amongst one another to see who
could organize the most elaborate games.
This in turn led to the creation of a
massive gladiatoral industry set to make
their dreams a reality. Thus, by the
late republic, hundreds of gladiators
and wild animals were being trotted out
before the crowds for multi-day events
with accompanying parades, feasts, and
parties. The disruption of the Surval
and civil wars temporarily slowed down
the rise of the gladiators. But once
peace was restored, their return was
inevitable. During the imperial period,
the games roared back to life, ascending
to new heights with such spectacles as
the massive Namakia of Augustus and
Claudius. Shortly thereafter came the
construction of the fame coliseum
capable of holding 80,000 spectators. It
is during this era of the golden age of
the gladiator which we shall set our
episode.
So the first thing we might want to know
is just how did one exactly get into the
coliseum to see one of these famous
games? Well, unlike the modern tourist
attraction, it wasn't open for visitors
every day of the week. Rather, the
coliseum would only open its doors to
the public on scheduled days. These
corresponded to certain festivals
throughout the year or celebratory
events like triumphs or the dedication
of new major building projects. One
surviving calendar from the 4th century
AD indicates that there were just 10
days of the year on which games were
scheduled, so roughly one a month on
average. However, on major occasions,
spectacles might actually run for 100
days on end, as was the case for
Trajan's victory over the Deian in 107
AD. That may seem like quite a lot, but
in reality, the games of the Colosseum
were eclipsed by the frequency of the
chariot races over in the Circus
Maximus.
So, let's say you were new in town. How
would you know when one of these big
days was approaching? Well, as it turns
out, that would be quite hard to miss.
Games of the Imperial period were highly
organized with dates being selected and
preparations being made months in
advance. The person in charge known as
the Aditor had their hands full. Beasts
had to be imported from exotic
locations. Gladiatorial schools had to
be contracted. Amenities had to be
acquired and everything had to be set up
just so. This flurry of activity would
send waves through the commercial world
as the orders of the adore were
fulfilled. In addition, you would also
see advertising campaigns for the event.
These consisted of hiring artists to
paint giant ads on buildings, producing
programs for the day, which listed the
events and stats of the gladiators, and
otherwise spreading news through word of
mouth. Here is one example of an ad
we've recovered from Pompei. Quote, "The
gladiator troop hired by Sudius Curteus
will fight in Pompei on May 31st. There
will also be a wild animal hunt. The
awnings will be used
As the day of the great event drew
closer, the social buzz would have been
inescapable, especially for the larger
events. This sort of word of mouth
excitement was exactly the sort of thing
that an editor was looking to create.
And it would not be surprising to find
out that they sent out volunteers or
paid staff to spread gossip and scratch
out evocative graffiti. In addition, an
aditor might set up small teaser events
to further generate buzz. Things like
walking a giraffe around the forum or
displaying caged beasts outside the
coliseum seem like no-brainer marketing
ploy.
All right, so now that the people know
when the games will occur, how would
they actually get in? Well, it turns out
that the Romans had a ticketing system
for designating seats much like our own
modern events. These typically consisted
of pottery shards with a listed entrance
gate, level, section, and row number.
Tickets were free for the masses and
would be distributed months in advance
to powerful individuals and groups who
would in turn disperse them as they saw
fit. However, considering that Rome had
a population far larger than could fit
in the coliseum, it's possible that not
everyone who wanted to go could do so.
In such situations, you might just have
to wait until the next availability.
Alternatively, there was an unofficial
market of scalpers collecting and
reselling tickets who you could seek
out. So maybe you knew a guy who knew a
guy who knew a guy that could get you
tickets for the big show and might even
get you better seats for a reasonable
price.
When the scheduled day arrived, you were
to come to the coliseum. Usually events
started in the morning and ended in the
evening, but really you could come and
go at any time. Perhaps you might show
up early to chat with some friends and
wander through the vendor stands that
had set up shop in the plaza outside.
Many would have been selling food and
drink with which to snack on during the
events. Others would be selling useful
items like mats, cushions, and umbrellas
to be brought into the arena. There were
also more exotic items for the super
fans. These included used weapons
thought to bring vitality, vials of
gladiator sweat that apparently went
into women's body oils or cosmetics, as
well as blood from slain fighters, which
would be used in wedding ceremonies and
other rituals.
Tucked away in other areas would be the
more illicit activities such as
gambling. Here you could bet on anything
from small games of dice to the outcomes
of upcoming gladiatorial matches.
Technically, such gambling was illegal
in Rome, but it became permissible on
certain festival days and at other times
the authorities merely turned a blind
eye. For example, we hear of how
Augustus himself once bet and lost
30,000 cycles on a gladiatorial match.
With so much financially at stake, it's
likely that investments were also being
made into magic and voodoo to sway the
outcome of events. This would have taken
the form of spells and curse tablets,
which were ubiquitous in the Roman
world, and which we covered in a
previous episode.
So, all this considered, there was
really a lot of ways you could have fun
and mischief at the coliseum without
ever going inside.
But for our purposes, let's assume we
are here for the games and are ready to
go in. The next step will be to proceed
to the correct gate marked on your
ticket. Finding the right one might take
a little time for newcomers as there
were 80 of them. Two were reserved for
the Imperial family, two for gladiators,
and the other 76 for spectators. If it
was a particularly busy day, you might
have to wait in line as the crowd
streamed in. However, the building was
engineered with plenty of stairways to
maximize traffic flow, and you shouldn't
have to wait too long before reaching
the ticket check and being allowed in.
Ancient sources claim that the whole
structure could be filled or emptied in
just 15 minutes.
Once inside, you would then proceed to
your designated level, either by asking
the way or referring to handy diagrams
on the wall. The levels were reflection
of the social order. The first tier, for
example, had arena side seating and a
luxurious setup. It was reserved for the
most important Romans, including the
emperor and his entourage, the royal
family, the vestal virgins, the
senators, and other nobles or religious
figures. So entrenched was their status
that these individuals and groups often
had their names actually carved into
their stone seating.
Behind them was the second tier, which
was reserved for non-senatorial
equestrians.
The third tier meanwhile held the
plebeians, the bulk of Rome's citizen
population.
And behind this, in the fourth and later
fifth tier held the poor, the
non-citizens, the foreigners, and the
women.
Generally, the further away you were,
the more bare and cramped your seating,
and at a certain point, there was only
standing room available.
Avid has a great passage that
illustrates the relatable experience of
a crowded arena quite well. Quote, "I'm
not sitting here because of my
enthusiasm for the events. I came here,
in fact, so that I might sit beside you
and talk to you. Why are you edging away
from me? It's no use. The seat marker
forces us to touch." Yes, the circus
does offer some advantages in its
seating rules. Hey, you on the right,
whoever you are, be more considerate of
the lady. You're hurting her by pressing
up against her. and you two behind us
drawing your legs if you have any sense
of decency and don't stick your bony
knees in her back.
So just as today there would be all the
usual drama in the stands. People would
flirt, joke, argue, gamble, eat, laugh,
belch, chant and brawl. There wasn't
much security at these events and at the
end of the day the unruly masses simply
did their thing. This drew some flak
from later Christian writers like
Clement of Alexandria who lamented the
promiscuous vices of the mingling crowd
of women and men arguing that such
events should therefore be banned. But
for everyone else, the social nature of
the games were part of their appeal.
So now that we found our seat, what can
we expect from the day? Well, you could
find the answer on the programs that had
been prepared for the event. But even
without these, it should be quite easy
to guess as the spectacles often
followed a predictable format that had
first been standardized by Augustus.
This had four basic parts. The pompa
which was an opening procession of the
showrunners and entertainers. The wenes
which were the morning beast hunts, the
miridani which was the lunch break often
involving executions. And the mona which
were the afternoon gladiatoral matches.
Let's now cover each of these in greater
detail.
The pompa kicked off the spectacles
officially with a standardized parade.
By tradition, the ltors of the editor
came first, followed by trumpeters,
whose fanfare would announce the bearers
of the gods, or at least idols of them.
Next would be the official scribes of
the spectacle, who would take the
records of the day's events, preserving
them for all posterity. Next came the
editor himself, parading in a manner of
his choosing. A mural from Pompei shows
an aditor entering with a parade of
horses. And it's not so much of a
stretch to imagine that chariots and
even elephants may have been used in
this capacity. Yet, no matter how hard
the organizer tried, the crowd would
always cheer louder for the true stars
of the show who came next, the
gladiators. With 80,000 people cheering
and the trumpets sounding off, it must
have been an insanely rockous event that
could be heard far beyond the walls of
the coliseum.
Once the parade had concluded, the
participants would disperse to their
respective stations. Now the winnes
could begin. These featured a wide array
of animals that would put the full scope
of the Roman Empire on display.
Spectators saw lions, tigers, leopards,
panthers, bears, elephants, rhinos,
apes, giraffes, zebras, crocodiles,
ostriches, seals, and more. They might
be trotted out through the gates or
lifted up dramatically through hidden
trap doors. To further add to the scene,
there might also have been plants and
terrain added to the arena to make it
seem like their natural environment,
almost like a zoo exhibit. Sometimes the
goal was just to have the exotic nature
of the animal speak for itself or to
have it perform a neat trick. This could
be as simple as having a seal balance a
ball on its nose.
One of my favorite anecdotes, though, is
the ludicrous mention of having trained
monkeys dawn soldiers armor and ride
around on goats as if they were doing
battle.
However, as entertaining as this might
be the first few times, the people
always wanted more sensational events,
which often meant having animals fight
one another or fight some humans. The
latter proved extremely popular and
often featured prominently on the ads of
the coliseum.
In these events, fierce beasts, often
trained to kill, would be pitted against
a wentor or hunter with nothing more
than light padding and a spear. It was a
true contest of skill on both sides,
with the added stakes that the human had
not just to survive, but to make a show
of it. In these duels, the crowd might
just as easily cheer on a hunter with a
string of victories under his belt, as
they would a notorious predator with a
bloody history to its name.
The level of animal killing in the games
is insane and numbered in the hundreds,
if not thousands slain for the
particularly large spectacles. So
bloodthirsty were the Romans that they
literally drove several species to
extinction due to the popularity of
these hunts. Eventually, as the sun rose
higher and higher and noon approached,
the massive awnings of the coliseum,
which were operated by the sailors,
would be unfurled. These help keep the
vast crowds cool while leaving a central
hole to illuminate the arena. In
addition, we hear of water pipes called
spariones that help pump water into the
arena and misted the entire area,
efficiently combating the heat.
Apparently, some emperors even added
perfumes to the water to create an even
more pleasing environment.
As the crowd began to cool off, both
physically and emotionally from the
morning events, they could now enjoy the
intermission known as the Meridiani.
This would be a good time to stretch
your legs, go to the bathroom, and grab
some water. Once more, there would be
vendors outside and throughout the
coliseum to meet your every need. In
true Roman fashion, there were even
prostitutes available. With no concern
for privacy, the nooks and crannies of
the building would be filled with people
either having sex or trying to sell it.
The archways, called fornices, are the
root of the English fornication for a
reason and were a popular diversion.
As you made your way back to your seat
or perhaps entered the coliseum for the
first time, you would also be presented
with the main scheduled event for the
lunch break, the execution of condemned
criminals that had been saved up for the
games. Hollywood likes to embellish
these, giving the embattled individuals
a chance at survival and freedom if they
won. In reality, though, the Romans were
not actually that merciful. Those who
went in to die almost never came back
alive.
While this was a near certainty, the
particular method of execution was up to
the organizer. As recounted by ancient
authors, these could be gruesomely
sadistic. For instance, Marshall tells
of a recreation of Prometheus with the
criminal being staked out and sliced
open for an oncoming beast. Another
time, performers were made to dance in
goddy clothes until gladiators emerged
to stab them and set them on fire. Some
were fed hungry beasts while one Roman
novel writes of a murderous who was
sentenced to be publicly raped by a
donkey before both were devoured by
lions. It was a truly brutal, brutal
spectacle.
While many in the crowd certainly
cheered, we have numerous ancient
authors who wrote in disgust about the
practice that lacked any redeeming
qualities of honor or bravery.
Eventually, after the hour or two of
intermission, it would be time for the
most popular events of the day, the Mona
or the gladiatorial matches. These were
the real appeal of the spectacles, and
it's at noon that the coliseum would
truly begin to fill to capacity.
Apparently, so many people swarmed in
that actors would complain regularly
that their spectators would vanish
almost instantly when a gladiator show
was about to begin.
The gladiators themselves came from
different backgrounds. Many were slaves
or criminals condemned to the arena,
while others might actually be paid
volunteers and freed men. Whatever the
case, they would often undergo some
training to make sure they put on a good
show. This typically meant specializing
in one of the more than 20 fighting
styles, including the heavily armed
Mormo or the light net wielding
Ratiarius. Different styles naturally
had their own pros and cons, and the
best fighters pitted various
combinations against one another for
dynamic action. This was especially
important when it came to the more
professional duels between masters of
their respective craft. Such fame
gladiators were celebrities who might
only have three to five public matches a
year. You would not want to miss these
when they came around.
Such bouts might last anywhere from just
a few minutes to upwards of 15. The pros
knew how to work the crowd with dazzling
moves which would in turn be even more
dramatized through the use of music to
build tension and sound off the hits. To
keep the high-end matches fair, there
were actually referees involved who
enforced rules, separated opponents, or
called an end to the fighting. Contrary
to popular belief, not every battle was
fought to the death. And many times a
gladiator could merely be bested in a
non-lethal manner or shown mercy. It was
really about the performance they gave.
For instance, if a fighter showed
cowardice or fought poorly, the crowd
might turn against them and begin to
chant for their punishment. When the mob
mentality of tens of thousands took
hold, there was little an emperor could
do but obey.
Once the deed was done and the poor soul
was dispatched, it was customary for an
attendant dressed as Chiron, the
fairyman of Hades, to strike the
defeated gladiator to confirm his death,
at which point he would be carded off.
In this way, the afternoon at the
coliseum would be filled with multiple
duels that often built up to your big
headliners. Along the way, small lulls
between matches would be opportunities
for the crowd to once again stretch
their legs, go to the bathroom, and grab
a bite. However, one reason to remain in
your seat would be the Sparion's
miselium, which were basically the
ancient equivalent to the t-shirt
cannon, only better. The way this worked
is that small wooden balls would be
filled with a piece of parchment that
could be redeemed for special prizes.
These could be anything from small
rewards of food or cash to truly
incredible valuables like silver, gold,
slaves, horses, elephants, and even
apartments or country estates. Emperors
were famous for their particular impish
sense of humor when it came to crafting
prizes. Elgabilis, for instance, amused
himself with having a range of prizes at
one event, from a bear to a dormis, and
from 10 cabbages to 10 lb of gold.
Needless to say, these were far more
popular than foul balls are today. And
when the masilia were brought out,
violence was soon to follow. Senica, for
instance, describes how they were used
at virtually all public entertainment
and that it was best to leave before
they started to be thrown. Herodian even
describes how it was common for people
to murder each other over catching the
prizes and how there were speculators
who hung outside the arena paying people
for unopened prizes.
This irony that this final bout of
violence was often orchestrated among
the audience themselves was lost on them
as well as the fact that the fights over
the prizes often led to the destruction
of the slip of paper that the prize was
on.
There will be much more to cover in our
series on gladiators, but for now, this
is where we will end our episode. I've
absolutely loved exploring the coliseum
from the audience's perspective and
continue to be amazed by just how
familiar many aspects of the past are to
us today. If you'd like to bring a piece
of that past home as well, you can
actually check out some of the merch
from our store, which we created to
celebrate A Day at the Games. These help
ensure we can keep making more awesome
documentaries. So, please consider a
purchase.
A huge thanks to the patrons as well for
funding the channel and to the
researchers, writers, and artists for
making this episode possible. Be sure to
like and subscribe for more content and
check out these other related episodes.
See you in the next one.